[Parinsula version 0.9.3: ReadMe.txt]

OVERVIEW

Parinsula provides a means of simulating and visualizing the behavior of several generic types of relatively isolated systems.

The nature of a particular relatively isolated system is determined largely by the quantity and quality of the semipermeable boundaries or membranes that it possesses and the resulting partially sheltered interior spaces that they create within the system. Such boundaries regulate the passage of objects and causal influences from the external environment into the system’s interior and from the system’s interior into the external environment.

NATURE OF THE MODELS

In the real world, there are myriad types of partially isolating structures, mechanisms, or behaviors that a given system might include and which (depending on the nature of the system) might operate at physical, cognitive, social, or other levels. Within the simplified models utilized by this simulator, there are three generic types of components that a system might possess, which give rise to semipermeable boundaries possessing varying characteristics:

• Reflectors repel any environmental objects that come into contact with them; external influences effectively “bounce” off of them.

• Absorbers arrest the motion of any environmental objects that come into contact with them but do not strongly repel the objects; such absorbers tend to “trap” any arriving objects.

• Transmitters allow environmental objects to pass through them with relative ease; the probability of an arriving object being obstructed by a transmitter are non-zero but relatively low.

The simulator provides models of five different relatively isolated systems, each of which includes a fixed central node surrounded by an array of (potentially) mobile components. The first three models present components that are uniformly of a single type (either Reflectors, Absorbers, or Transmitters). The final two models present systems that include a mix of all three types of components.

NAVIGATION AND MANIPULATION OF THE MODELS

Use the buttons at the bottom of the screen to load one of the five models. You can then use your mouse wheel to zoom in and out on the currently active model or left-click and drag in order to pan the view.

The attractive force exerted by the system’s central node can be adjusted (with a range spanning 0.01 to 4 units) using the on-screen slider. Depending on the value of that force, a system’s components can create boundaries demonstrating varying degrees of cohesion and permeability.

For reference purposes, the counters in the upper right corner of the screen indicate the amount of time elapsed (in seconds) for the current model, along with the total number of updates (which may be thought of roughly as “iterations”) produced by the model.

THE THEORETICAL FOUNDATIONS OF RELATIVELY ISOLATED SYSTEMS

The concept of the “relatively isolated system” was developed by Polish philosopher Roman Ingarden (1893-1970) and explored in a number of his works, including:

• Ingarden, Roman. Spór o istnienie świata, vol. I. Kraków: Polskie Akademia Umiejętności, 1947.
• Ingarden, Roman. Spór o istnienie świata, vol. II. Kraków: Polskie Akademia Umiejętności, 1948.
• Ingarden, Roman. Über die Verantwortung: Ihre ontischen Fundamente. Stuttgart: Reclam, 1970.
• Ingarden, Roman. Über die kausale Struktur der realen Welt: Der Streit um die Existenz der Welt III. Tübingen: Max Niemeyer Verlag, 1974.

The concept of the relatively isolated system bears some resemblance to Bertalanffy’s concept of the “open” system” (and after having become familiar with Bertalanffy’s thought, Ingarden cites and analyzes it in some of his later systems-theoretical writings); however, there are also significant differences between the two concepts.

Although Ingarden is known today primarily for his ontology, aesthetics, and philosophical anthropology, his concept of the relatively isolated system has proven significant enough to earn him a place as one of the most influential Polish systems theorists and cyberneticists of the 20th Century. (For discussion of that point, see P. Sienkiewicz and R. Wojtala, “Systems Thinking in Poland,” in Systems Thinking in Europe, M. Jackson et al., eds., New York: Plenum Press, 1991, pp. 197-99.) Ingarden’s systems theory has contemporary applications in such diverse fields as theoretical biology, architecture, and computer game design.

Parinsula is developed and published by Cognitive Firewall LLC. The software was designed by Matthew E. Gladden.

————————————————————